<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>As Iheronimus, sheweth in this begynnynge, so wyll I wryte of the .iiij. tokens the whiche shall be shewed afore the dredefull daye of dome, of our lorde Ihesu Christe. For there shall we shewe ourself yonge and olde, [and]c.</title>
            <title>Four tokens of judgement</title>
            <author>Jerome, Saint, d. 419 or 20.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14505</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100689</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04385)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>As Iheronimus, sheweth in this begynnynge, so wyll I wryte of the .iiij. tokens the whiche shall be shewed afore the dredefull daye of dome, of our lorde Ihesu Christe. For there shall we shewe ourself yonge and olde, [and]c.</title>
                  <title>Four tokens of judgement</title>
                  <author>Jerome, Saint, d. 419 or 20.</author>
                  <author>Doesborch, Jan van, d. 1536.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by me Robert Wyer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1535?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Saint Jerome.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 68 &amp; 69) on B4v, final page.</note>
                  <note>Translated out of Dutch into English by Jan van Dousbrugh [i.e. Doesborch].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgement Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:797:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>¶As Iheroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſheweth In this begynnynge, ſo wyll I wryte of the .iiij. Tokens, the whiche ſhall be ſhewed afore the dredefull daye of Dome, of our lorde Iheſu Chriſte. For there ſhall we ſhewe ourſelf yonge and olde. &amp;c. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:797:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ihero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus.</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of St. Jerome</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:797:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND oure Lorde, wyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhalbe ſhewed .iiij. toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after doctours ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, For our lorde is ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull that he wyl not punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe vs but he wyl ſhewe ſome tokens afore. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye be ſory of our ſynnes, and do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And after theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde .iiij. tokens ſhall yet be xv. other tokens be ſhewed. which Iheronimus had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the rinſkens Cronicle of the Iewes. Of whiche .xv. tokens foreſayde ſhall be declared by order here after.</p>
               <p>¶And the fyrſte token of the iiij. ſhalbe that the myght of
<pb facs="tcp:797:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
Sathan through the paſſion of our lorde was made laſſer, and was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den, and ſhalbe vnbonden. All be it that he by the myght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſion be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, and may not do ſo moche harme to the menſhen as he was wonte to do. But the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den at certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes, and he ſhalbe vnbou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den that he may do the more harme to the people with temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; trybulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to aſſaye them tho that be choſen.</p>
               <p>¶But in the laſt tyme of the worlde, ſhall the good be very good, &amp; the euyll, ſhalbe very badde. Lyke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy wryters ſhewe in the laſt chaptre of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalipſis.
<pb facs="tcp:797:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
¶Tempus prope eſt qui nocet noceat ad huc et qui i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſordibus eſt ſordeſcat ad huc. et iuſtus iuſtificetur, ad huc et qui ſanctus eſt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficetur, ad huc.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>¶The .ij. token.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſeconde token, of the foure, ſhalbe, as loue ſhall be loſte, &amp; nomore be vſed. Ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kewyſe, as the menſhen wax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en olde, and the nature wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth colde in them, whiche the Philoſopher calleth it the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell world. Lykewyſe is it of the great world. who the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the ende, The more the loue waxeth colde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:797:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
her ſelf. But the herte of a bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is ghoſtly of lyuyng in the greatter worlde. And ſhal al hole fayle, for it gothe ſore to the ende of the worlde. As a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolus ad hebreos. Qui an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiquatur et ſe neſcit prope in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritum eſt. And a man maye nowe knowe howe that god is ſeruyd without deuocion. And how he is blaſphemyd, and by them ſweryng, and al ſo pull hym all a ſonder in pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. And ye may well knowe that the loue is almoſte done and is waxen colde, and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed awaye, but ſome be naked, and pray hertely, but they fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de no helpe, And they that be
<pb facs="tcp:797:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
hungery dye for hunger, and haue no ſocoure. The gate of mercy is ſhytte, the fountey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of compaſſyon hath ſhytte her conduytes. And through fayled amonge his frendes, &amp; ſhe ſhall not be founden afore God ſhall gyue ſentence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that haue hunted cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and pacyence out of this worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>¶The thyrde token.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thyrde Token, ſhalbe as al maner of euyll and ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, ſhalbe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world, &amp; the fere of God be put dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; haue none thynkyng on hym. And whan faythfull &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:797:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
pacyence ſhall not be ſet by: but all maner of euyll ſhalbe vſed: and whan the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſchen ſhulde loue with a ſecrete lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and care of no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but for her owne profyte. And alſo we ſhall be afore the ende of the worlde: be poude and hye ſhall make moche of theym ſelfe: and ſhall blaſpheme the name of the Lorde, and they ſhal not care of Father or mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and than they ſhall loue fleſſhely nature more thanne God. As the Apoſtle in the .ij. Epiſtle of Thimotheum.</p>
               <p>¶Therfore lette euery body reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre in theym ſelfe what people now a dayes be lyuyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:797:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
in this worlde, &amp; loke well yf this aforeſayd thynges be not nowe a dayes ſhewed &amp; done, and ſet by no ſynne. For it is not well poſſyble that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bodye myghte wryte the great ſynnes that now a day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es be done Praye we to God that he wyll come to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they maye do penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce afore theyr departynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="token">
               <head>¶ The fourth token.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth Token, that ſhalbe before the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, and afore the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther .xv. tokens, &amp; afore the great orryble day of Dome. And than ſhall there
<pb facs="tcp:797:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
be great peruerten and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and there ſhalbe warre in many dyuers Landes of the worlde, and alſo amonge all creatures in this worlde ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng. For as Matheus ſayth in the .xiiij. Chapter. Fightyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and warres ſhalbe amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vs, and alſo one body ſhall aryſe agaynſt the other, and alſo one kynge agaynſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and alſo treaſon ſhalbe in cyties and townes, yet for all that they made peas, and peas ſhall be throughout the world, &amp; layde downe agayn, and vp with warre agayne, throughout the worlde: and alſo the Prynce agaynſt his
<pb facs="tcp:797:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons: and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hym. Alſo there ſhall be no clouſter of Monkes, nor of Nonnes, yet there ſhall be ful of peruertes contrary one the ocher. And than ſhal it be as Iheremias wryteth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his .x. chapter. Vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſe a ſuo proximo cuſtodiat. That is for to ſay Euery man kepe hym of his neyghbour or fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: and truſte not in his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for one ſhall ſhewe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a fayre face, but the herte of hym is full falſe, And alſo one brother ſhall mocke that other, and he ſhall laye ſnares and grynnes for hym, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle hym yf he may. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:797:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
is it fulfylled lyke. Meſſin as the Prophet ſayde, Kepe you of, beware you of your owne wyfe, the whiche ſlepeth in your armes all nyght, for ſhe ſhal begyle her owne huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. And alſo the childe ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyle the Father: and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the childe: &amp; the dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the mother: and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the doughter. And alſo one brother ſhall delyuer the other to death. And the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſone, and the children the father. And whan all the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thynges &amp; peruerten ſhall be throughout all the worlde Than great men and meane men ſhal loke for theyr owne
<pb facs="tcp:797:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
Synguler welth, and not for no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, for they ſhal ſcrape twenty mens lyuyng, or a hondred, and care not for the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of our Lorde Iheſu chriſte, ſayeng they hym regarde not a whyt Than ſhall it be a Token of the laſte Termyne, or ende of this world. Other peruerten ſhalbe in the fyrmament: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly it ſhalbe a dere tyme. not alone in one prouynce, or kyngdome, but throughoute all the worlde: but it ſhall be that the earth ſhall bere none fruyte to our behoufe, or nede to lyue with all. And it ſhall be alſo great earthquakes be
<pb facs="tcp:797:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
agaynſt all nature, that there ſhall fallen downe Caſtels &amp; howſes. And alſo in the ſee &amp; ryuers ſhalbe more peruerten than it hath be afore, And the eyer ſhalbe full of corrupcion and venym, therof ſhal come great Peſtilence, as well i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beeſts as in the menſhen ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of: they ſhall dye. And alſo it ſhalbe thonderynge, &amp; lyghte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge, and great tempeſtes, and wyndes ſhalbe more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryllous than they were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to be. And the people ſhall before aferde. And lykewyſe as ſeynt Iheronimus hathe founde in the .xv. pryncipall tokens, they ſhalbe afore the
<pb facs="tcp:797:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
dredefull day of Dome, of our Lorde Iheſus chriſte.</p>
               <p>¶But we know not yf theſe xv. Tokens ſhall be ſhewed one after another, or yf there ſhalbe any other token ſhall be ſhewed betwene. Therof ſayde ſeynt Iheronimus, no certeyne, nor no Doctour, but they put it in the wyll of oure Lorde, but our Lorde maye therwith doo his wyll, for he is almyghtye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶This tranſlated out of Duche into Englyſſhe, by Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Douſbrugh.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted by me Robert Wyer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printers_device">
            <pb facs="tcp:797:9"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>ROBERT <figure>
                        <figDesc>merchant's monogram</figDesc>
                     </figure> WYER.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:797:9"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
